Grüezi YouTubers.
Here is the guy with the Swiss accent.
With a new episode around sensors and microcontrollers.
In video #133 we used super capacitors to
safely shutdown the Rapberry Pi.
In the comments, viewers asked about over
voltage protection of the super caps.
I will show you a big and small and cheap
possibility.
And I will show you one concept which does
not really work.
But why do we have to protect Super Capacitors?
And how can we protect them?
Most Super capacitors are only specified up
to 2.7 volt.
If we need higher voltages, we have to connect
a few of them in series.
To give the Raspberry a save shutdown I used
two caps because it runs on 5 volt USB.
So, the basic diagram is like that: Two Super
capacitors in series across the 5 volt connector.
If we charge now capacitors in series, the
current is equal in both capacitors.
But, if the capacitance are not completely
equal, the one with the lower capacitance
charges faster and its voltage can go over
the rated 2.7 volts.
To avoid that, we have to connect a resistor
in parallel to the smaller capacitor.
Like that, part of the current can flow through
this resistor and therefore is not used for
overcharging the capacitor.
Because we do not know, which of the capacitors
is smaller and exactly how much, and because
some other things can happen, we add a small
switch to this resistor.
It switches only, if the voltage of the capacitor
is close to the 2.7 volt.
Like that, we can use quite small resistors
and bypass a big amount of the current.
As soon as the voltage is in the save zone,
the resistor is switched off again.
If we use such a concept for all our capacitors,
and our protection voltage is 2.7 volt, they
are protected against over voltage as long
as the total voltage is lower than the number
of capacitors times 2.7.
In our case, the voltage would have to stay
below 5.4 volts.
Which is ok with USB.
The specification allows a maximum voltage
of 5.2 volts.
Let’s start with the simplest concept: Zener
diodes.
The easiest way would be to solder a Zener
diode across each super cap.
But what is a Zener diode?
Normal diodes conduct current only in one
direction and block it in the other direction
(at least up to their very high blocking voltage).
Zener diodes are somehow different.
In principle, they also block current in the
“wrong” direction up to a certain voltage.
But this voltage is low and exactly specified.
You can get Zener diodes for many voltages.
If we check one with our transistor tester,
it shows two diodes in opposite direction.
The one with the voltage of 0.8 volt is the
normal diode.
The other one with 2.4 volt is the Zener part.
Let’s have a closer look: On the positive
voltage side, we see a curve of a normal diode.
On the negative voltage side, we see the Zener
behavior.
At the beginning, nearly no current flows.
At a particular voltage, the current starts
to flow.
But this is not at a sharp voltage as we can
see.
The curve is only bent.
Because all these things happen on the negative
voltage side, we have to use the Zener diodes
always in reverse direction.
This is, why I mirror the curve now.
Just a small remark: Not all transistor testers
are able to measure Zener diodes properly.
And all can only detect these diodes if they
have a low Zener voltage.
So, let’s check how this simple concept
works.
I have 2.4 volt and 2.7 volt Zeners.
I start my test with no protection at all.
Two 10 Farad Super Caps are connected in Series
and 5 volt is applied.
If both are discharged at the beginning, they
load quite evenly.
The difference is small, because their capacities
are similar.
I discharge now the left capacitor a little
to simulate uneven capacities.
If I load them again, the right one quickly
approaches 2.7 volts and I have to stop the
experiment in order to not harm it.
Let’s now protect this Cap with a 2.4 volt
Zener.
To understand what happens, I measure the
current through the diode with the yellow
Fluke meter.
As we already know from the chart, the diode
already starts to conduct at below 2.4 volt.
So, a part of the current is now “diverged”
through the diode instead of the capacitor.
This part does not charge the capacitor anymore.
So, the other cap can catch up.
But because the current through the diode
is quite small, the protection is not big,
and the voltage exceed 2.7 volts a little.
If the imbalance between the two capacitors
would be bigger, this protection would not
work anymore.
And, we easily can imagine, that a 2.7 volt
Zener would not work at all.
So, this is a simple protection, which works
somehow for these small capacitors.
But fortunately, we have a better one: The
TL431.
This part is called “Precision Programmable
Reference” and it is a very versatile part
which can used for many applications.
It is also quite cheap: 50 pieces for 1.20,
including shipping.
It is even cheaper than a 2.4 volt Zener,
where 50 pieces cost more than 3 dollars.
The TL431 is a neat small part in a TO-92
package.
Its symbol looks much like a Zener diode,
with the exception that it has three pins
instead of only two.
The third pin is called REFERENCE.
If we look at the block diagram of the chip,
we see, that it consists of a precise 2.5
volt reference and an Opamp used as a comparator.
As soon as the reference voltage is above
the 2.5 volt, the transistor switches on.
So, if we connect the REFERENCE and the cathode
pins, we get this diagram.
Because I mirrored the diagram of the Zener
diode, both are compatible.
We have the positive voltage to the right
and positive current up.
We immediately see the difference: The bend
of the TL431 is much sharper.
At exactly 2.5 volts it starts to conduct
up to its maximum rating of 150 mA.
This is nearly the curve we were looking for.
The only thing is, that it is at 2.5 instead
of 2.7 volts.
So, let’s try out and replace the 2.4 volt
Zener with the TL431.
We also start with unevenly charged capacitors
and see, that the current through the TL431
starts to increase much more and much sharper
at 2.5 volts.
The voltage across the super cap still goes
above 2.5 volt, because the parts are not
ideal.
But still, the behavior is much better.
At the end, the protected and the unprotected
caps each show around 2.5 volts.
If I would now increase the voltage to 5.3
volt, only the unprotected cap’s voltage
would increase and would exceed its specified
voltage.
Which is obviously not good.
So, we could protect both capacitors.
Which anyway would be a good idea, because
we do not know, which one has a smaller capacity.
Below 5 volt total voltage, this would work
fine.
But as soon as we cross these 5 volts, both
TL431 would start to conduct and produce a
short cut.
They would heat up, and maybe even would destroy
themselves.
Maybe you remember the word “programmable”
from the description of the TL431?
Programmable means, that we can change the
“Zener voltage” with a simple trick: We
connect the reference pin to a voltage divider.
Now, the reference measures a lower voltage
and therefore, reaches the 2.5 volts at a
higher voltage.
If we calculate our resistors with the formula
from the data sheet, we can set the cutoff
voltage to 2.7 volt.
Problem solved!
If you really want to make sure, that nothing
bad happens to your protectors, you can add
a small series resistor.
Like that, the current through the TL431 is
limited.
If you plan to work only with USB voltages,
this is not necessary.
So, this is a great concept to protect small
super caps when you are sure, that the two
capacities are similar.
To show you the limitations, I double the
capacitance of one capacitor by adding a second
one.
Now, we see, that the current through the
TL431 gets quite high, and the voltage crosses
2.7 volt, even with a cutoff voltage of 2.5
volt.
To avoid that, I bought the voltage protectors
shown in the last Mailbag video #137.
They can be used for large capacitors up to
500 Farad.
I re-engineered its PCB and its diagram is
here.
They also use a TL431, but they use a big
transistor to amplify the effect.
So, let’s check, if it works.
I keep the “tougher” scenario with the
two uneven capacitors and protect the smaller
one.
Now with a protection board instead of the
TL431.
The rest stays the same.
Here, the protection kicks in at 2.66 volt
and the voltage never exceeds this value . The
other capacitor can easily catch up.
And if we would have two such protection boards
in series, our USB voltage could go up to
2 times 2.66 volt = 5.32 volt, which is above
USB specs anyway.
Summarized:
We wanted to protect our Super capacitors
against over voltage
The first concept using simple Zener diodes
worked somehow, but with very narrow limitations
The usage of a TL431 Precision Programmable
Reference did what we wanted for our small
capacitors, and even at lower cost.
With a voltage divider, we were able to set
the protection voltage at the right level.
We looked at the diagram of a commercial product
for larger capacitors and discovered, that
they also use a TL431
The commercial product worked too, and, because
it supports much bigger currents, can also
be used for bigger capacitors.
BTW: If we do the calculation of the voltage
divider of the protection board, we find the
2.66 volts we measured before.
Not bad!
I hope, this video was useful or at least
interesting for you.
If true then like.
Bye